A Guide to the Rives Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10596
Rives Family Papers ca. 1829-1923
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
10596
278 items
Laurens H. Rhinelander
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was made a gift to the Library by Laurens H. Rhinelander of Charlottesville, Virginia, on June 11, 1984.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of 278 items, ca. 1829-1923, chiefly pertaining to the activities of members of the Rives, Sears, and Rhinelander families of Virginia, Massachusetts, and New York, respectively. The papers include correspondence, business and legal papers, genealogical papers, a diary, photographs, newspaper clippings, and memorabilia. The correspondence chiefly is between members of the Rives family, especially William Cabell Rives(1793-1868), Judith Page Walker Rives(1802-1882), William Cabell Rives, Jr.(1825-1889), Grace Winthrop Sears Rives(1828-), and William Cabell Rives(1850-1938), and, to a lesser extent, Sears and Rhinelander family members. Other correspondents include Lewis Minor Coleman(1827-1863), Edward Everett(1794-1865), Joseph Grinnell(1788-1885), William Mahone(1826-1895), Thomas Walker Page(1866-1937), Sir Lyon Playfair(1818-1898), and the Rev. Cornelius Walker(1819-1907).
Topics of interest in the correspondence include: politics; life at the University of Virginia; life in Paris, France; travelling through Germany; William Cabell Rives, Jr.'s farm in Cobham; and the Civil War. A March 22, 1845, letter from New Orleans, Louisiana, in the Rhinelander correspondence, tells of being pulled along the Baratania Canal by slaves, and visiting the Bachelor establishment on the nearby plantation. Political activities are discussed in Alexander Rives' December 3, 1834, letter to William Cabell Rives pertaining to the latter's senatorial race and the principle of instruction, and in William Cabell Rives' letters to his wife, Judith, concerning politics in Washington during 1844. In a letter dated January 17, 1846, Lewis Minor Coleman writes William Cabell Rives, Jr., from the University of Virginia about the Jefferson Society and living on the East Range, then known as "Rowdy Row." Letters written to William Cabell Rives and William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1863-1868, are often concerned with the Civil War and its effects, especially on Southerners; and, in a letter written to his wife, Grace, on June 19, 1865, William Cabell Rives, Jr., refers to the "destruction of slavery." In her letters, 1851-1852, to Grace Winthrop Sears Rives, Judith Page Walker Rives reveals much about Paris, France, during the 1851 coup d'etat and establishment of the Second Empire under Louis Napoleon. Also, during 1851, William Cabell Rives, Jr., writes his mother while travelling in Germany, describing several cities. Various aspects of life in Cobham, Virginia, are revealed in N. B. Layne's 1853 letters to William Cabell Rives, Jr., concerning the management of the latter's estate, and in Judith Page Walker Rives' December 30, 1855, letter to Grace Winthrop Sears Rives describing the family's old fashioned Christmas party, as well as in letters of other members of the Rives family written from their home in Cobham. Correspondence between E. S. McSparran and William Cabell Rives, Jr., during 1854-1855 concern alterations in the plan of the latter's Albemarle County house, Cobham Park, and includes estimates and contracts.
Items of interest include a diary, 1860-1909, kept by Grace Winthrop Sears Rives, with many references to members of the Amory, Grant, Page, Rhinelander, Rives, and Sears families, and mentioning others, including Rev. F. K. Aglionby, William C. Dabney(1849-1894), Anne Cutler Hinckley(1813-1898), Einle George Money, Sir Lyon Playfair(1818-1898), and Bishop Henry Yates Satterlee(1843-1908). There appears to be much information useful to genealogical research. In addition, there is a letter of commendation from the French Republic, to Philip Newbold Rhinelander( -1918), for his service with the American Field-Hospital, accompanied by a commemorative medal presented to him.
Organization
The collection has been divided into four series: I. Correspondence; II. Business and Legal Papers; III. Miscellaneous and Genealogical Papers; and IV. Oversize. The material in this collection has been filed chronologically within each series. Correspondence is filed by correspondent.
Container List
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence of the Rhinelander family, 1829 (1862-1863) 1908, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Alexander Rives to William Cabell Rives and Judith Page Walker Rives, 1832-1834 (Box Box 1)
  - William F. Ritchie to William Cabell Rives, 1834 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters to Judith Page Walker Rives, 1841, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - William Cabell Rives to George Rives, 1843 (Box Box 1)
  - William Cabell Rives to Judith Page Walker Rives, 1844 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters to Introduction for William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1844 (Box Box 1)
  - Edward Everett to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1846 (Box Box 1)
  - William Cabell Rives, Jr. to William Cabell Rives, 1846 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1846-1865 (Box Box 1)
  - William Cabell Rives, Jr. to Hiram Sanders, 1848 (Box Box 1)
  - Robert Sears and David Sears to William Cabell Rives, 1849 (Box Box 1)
  - P[at] Grant and E[lizabeth] W. Grant to Grace Winthrop Sears Rives, 1849-1852, 1868 (Box Box 1)
  - Judith Page Walker Rives to Grace Winthrop Sears Rives, 1849-1858 (Box Box 1)
  - Fred R. Sears and Ellen Sears to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1850 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters to Grace Winthrop Sears Rives, 1850, 1872-1876, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - William Cabell Rives, Jr. to Judith Page Walker Rives, 1851 (Box Box 1)
  - Amelie Louise Rives to Grace Winthrop Sears Rives, 1852, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - N. B. Layne to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1853 (Box Box 1)
  - Thomas W. Agee to William Cabell Rives, 1853 (Box Box 1)
  - E. S. McSparran to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1854-1855 (Box Box 1)
  - Judith Page Walker Rives to William Cabell Rives (3rd), 1856, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - William Cabell Rives, Jr. to Grace Winthrop Sears Rives, 1857-1865, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - K[uyvett] W. Sears to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1860, 1864 (Box Box 1)
  - Judith Page Walker Rives to Grace Winthrop Sears Rives, 1860-1869 (Box Box 1)
  - George Rives to William Cabell Rives, 1863 (Box Box 1)
  - Little, Brown, and Company to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1863, 1868 (Box Box 1)
  - Thomas Donaldson and Captain John H. McCue to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1865 (Box Box 1)
  - J. B. MacMurdo to William Cabell Rives, 1867 (Box Box 1)
  - William Mahone to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1867 (Box Box 1)
  - Charles Morris to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1867-1868 (Box Box 1)
  - Judith Page Walker Rives to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1868-1871 (Box Box 1)
  - Ella Rives to Grace Winthrop Sears Rives, 1869 (Box Box 1)
  - Judith Page Walker Rives to Grace Winthrop Sears Rives, 1870-1872 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1870-1885 (Box Box 1)
  - Francis Robert Rives to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1871 (Box Box 1)
  - William Cabell Rives (3rd) to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1872-1873, 1881, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Letters to William Cabell Rives (3rd), 1872-1918 (Box Box 1)
  - Judith Page Walker Rives to William Cabell Rives, Jr. and Amelie Louise Rives Sigourney, 1873-1874 (Box Box 2)
  - Judith Page Walker Rives to Grace Winthrop Sears Rives, 1873-1876 (Box Box 2)
  - William Cabell Rives, Jr. to William Cabell Rives (3rd), 1874 (Box Box 2)
  - Richard D. Sears to William Cabell Rives (3rd), 1876 (Box Box 2)
  - William Cabell Rives, Jr. to Frederick R. Sears, 1878 (Box Box 2)
  - Sir Lyon Playfair to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1879 (Box Box 2)
  - Samuel Powel and J. Truman Burdick to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1880 (Box Box 2)
  - Einle George Money to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1884 (Box Box 2)
  - Rev. C[ornelius] Walker to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1884 (Box Box 2)
  - Thomas Walker Page to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1885 (Box Box 2)
  - Grace Winthrop Sears Rives to William Cabell Rives (3rd), 1893-1894 (Box Box 2)
  - A[lfred] L[andon] Rives to Grace Winthrop Sears Rives, 1896 (Box Box 2)
  - Amelie Rives Troubetzkoy to William Cabell Rives (3rd), 1899 (Box Box 2)
  - William Cabell Rives (3rd) to Grace Winthrop Sears Rives, 1899 (Box Box 2)
  - William Cabell Rives (3rd) to "My dear Bishop" [Philip Mercer Rhinelander], n.d. [ca. 1923?] (Box Box 2)
  - Judith Page Walker Rives to Grace Winthrop Sears Rives, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - Fred[eric] [R. Sears] to "My dear Frank", n.d. (Box Box 2)
- Business and Legal Papers
  - Business Papers of William Cabell Rives, 1832-1838 (Box Box 2)
  - Business Papers of William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1853-1887 (Box Box 2)
  - Last Wills and Testaments of William Cabell Rives and Judith Page Walker Rives, 1866, 1875 (Box Box 2)
  - Last Will and Testament, and Deed of Sale, of Grace Winthrop Sears Rives, 1873, 1909, 1913 (Box Box 2)
  - Business Papers of William Cabell Rives (3rd), 1888-1916 (Box Box 2)
- Miscellaneous and Genealogical Material
  - Remarks of William Cabell Rives made in Congress, 1827, 1836 (Box Box 2)
  - Scenes of Newport, Rhode Island (postcards), 1850 (Box Box 2)
  - Diary of Grace Winthrop Sears Rives, 1860-1909 (Box Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings re the Rhinelander, Rives, Sears, and related families, 1864-1919, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1879, 1984, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - Cabell Family History, 1886-1891 (Box Box 2)
  - Founders Certificate and Letter of Commendation for Philip Newbold Rhinelander, 1899, 1910 (Box Box 2)
  - Prospectus for Mrs. Z. Mead's Boarding and Day School for Young Ladies in Richmond, Virginia (Box Box 2)
  - Religious Versus, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - Unidentified Photographs (Carte-de-Visites, Tintypes); and, Printing Plate for a Calling Card for William Cabell Rives, Jr. (Box Box 2)
  - Commemorative Medal given to Philip N[ewbold] Rhinelander by the French Republic, 1910 June 11 (Box Mini-tray)
- Oversize
  - Map of Lots to be Leased ... Belonging to the Heirs of William Rhinelander, Deceased (Box Oversize)